<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Shinyzenith</title>
    <link>https://aakash.is-a.dev/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Shinyzenith</description>
    <image>
      <url>https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/60808802?v=4</url>
      <link>https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/60808802?v=4</link>
    </image>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aakash.is-a.dev/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Wayland Compositor written in nim.</title>
      <link>https://aakash.is-a.dev/blogs/tinywl_nim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash.is-a.dev/blogs/tinywl_nim/</guid>
      <description>Recently I started an orgnization named Waycrate to write high quality wayland tools. Being drunk in the wayland craze I took it upon myself to rewrite BSPWM for Wayland. Since the waycrate team has already finished rewriting sxhkd for wayland, this makes my work a tad bit simpler.
I have decided to name the window manager HerbWM which uncomfyhalomacro came up with.
The futhark library has done nothing but shock me with it&amp;rsquo;s fantastic support for C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UNIX domain socket IPC in Rust.</title>
      <link>https://aakash.is-a.dev/blogs/unix_ipc_rust/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash.is-a.dev/blogs/unix_ipc_rust/</guid>
      <description>The IPC patch is complete and has been merged into the main branch.
The patch was made possible with the interprocess crate and was later rewritten to raw stdlib implementation in this commit. Currently the server binary (swhks) makes a socket at /run/user/(YourUserID)/swhkd.sock which then the daemon binary (swhkd) tries to establish a connection with.
After merging the initial set of patches Ckyiu found 2 issues right away:
Calling the function physical_path() on any evdev::Device object returns None on virtual machines and hence the binary panics and crashes while attempting to execute .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rewriting swhkd in rust!</title>
      <link>https://aakash.is-a.dev/blogs/swhkd_rust_rewrite/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash.is-a.dev/blogs/swhkd_rust_rewrite/</guid>
      <description>Hi all! It&amp;rsquo;s high time I put this domain purchase to use and uploaded my first blog.
I started a project called swhkd a few weeks back which stands for the Simple Wayland HotKey Daemon.
Swhkd is a drop in replacement for the popular X11 utility sxhkd, which is a hotkey daemon. Don&amp;rsquo;t let the name fool you, swhkd is compatible with X11, WayLand, and TTY.
Initially I wrote a python prototype which worked well for a concept but was a memory hog, consuming upto 19Mb for just printing the device key events.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://aakash.is-a.dev/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash.is-a.dev/about/</guid>
      <description>about</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PGP</title>
      <link>https://aakash.is-a.dev/pgp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://aakash.is-a.dev/pgp/</guid>
      <description>pgp</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
